Guide to the Fifth Decade Program Records, 1964-1973
University Archives Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Fifth Decade Program records 1964-1973
University Archives, Duke University
Duke University. Fifth Decade Program.
1.5 Linear Feet approx. 750 Items
The Fifth Decade Program was part of a ten-year plan to expand educational and research programs, strengthen the faculty, and upgrade the physical plant.
The collection includes the files of the Ad Hoc Committee on Quality, reports, printed material and clippings. It ranges in date from 1964-1973.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Collection is open for research.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Fifth Decade Program Records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1973.
Historical Note
The Fifth Decade Program was formally announced on March 10, 1965, but its origins may be found in the long range planning begun during the administration of President Edens. The fund-raising campaign was part of a ten-year plan to expand educational and research programs, strenghten the faculty, and upgrade the physical plant. A Special Trustee Committee on Duke's Fifth Decade was established in 1964 and a goal of $187,411,000 was set.
The Ad Hoc Committee on Quality in Relation to the Fifth Decade was established in Summer 1965 and was charged with examining how to maintain and improve the quality of the University, given that the enrollment was going to increase. The Committee was chaired by Arlin Turner and submitted its report to the University Policy and Planning Advisory Committee on May 3, 1966.
Collection Overview
The collection includes reports, memoranda, correspondence, brochures, clippings, and other materials concerning the fund-raising campaign undertaken during President Knight's administration. The bulk of the collection consists of printed reports but in addition includes records of the Ad Hoc Committee on Quality in Relation to the Fifth Decade. Those records of the Ad Hoc Committee on Quality were official transfers. The provenance of other material is conjectural and is not considered to be official transfers. The material ranges in date from 1964-1973.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Duke University. Fifth Decade Program
Duke University. Fifth Decade Program. Ad Hoc Committee on Quality in Relation to the Fifth Decade
Fund raising -- North Carolina -- Durham
Related Material
Office of University Development Records
Duke University Archives
Office of Institutional Advancement Records
Duke University Archives
Douglas M. Knight Records
Duke University Archives
A. Hollis Edens Records
Duke University Archives
Contents of Collection
- Ad Hoc Committee on Quality, 1965-1966
  - Correspondence, 1965-1966 (Box 1)
  - Report of the Ad Hoc Committee on Quality in Relation to the Fifth Decade, 1966
  - Report Drafts, 1965-1966
  - Ad Hoc Committee Report Notes, circa 1965-1966
  - University Committee on Long Range Planning, Report of Subcommittee on the Undergraduate Colleges, 1960
- Communications and Reports, 1965-1973
  - Communications, 1965-1966, 1968, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Summary Report through 1968 Nov. 30
  - Report and Recommendations to the Board of Trustees, 1965
  - University Report, 1966-1971
  - Campaign Report, 1966-1971
- Printed Materials, 1964-1971
  - Promotional (booklets, brochures, pamphlets), circa 1965-1969 (Box 2)
  - Duke University Today, 1967
  - School Brochures, 1966-1969
  - The Fifth Decade Campaign in Retrospective, 1965-1971
  - Chairman's Handbook, undated
  - Memorial Gift Opportunities, undated
  - A Statement of the Case for Duke University's Plans for the Future, 1965
  - THE FIFTH DECADE, rough copy, draft two
  - THE FIFTH DECADE, final draft[?], 1964
  - THE FIFTH DECADE, 1964 (Box 3)
  - THE FIFTH DECADE, 1964
- Miscellaneous, 1965-1966
  - A Staff Re-Examination, 1965[?] (Box 3)
  - Fund Raising Potentials for Duke University: A Survey, Analysis and Plan, John Price Jones Co., Inc., 1965
  - Clippings, 1965-1966